If I switch to management now, will I
just become a middle manager? Then like
I've stopped providing value. This is
Simon. He grew from a new grad to a
staff engineer at Meta in 3 years,
earning the highest ratings twice. And
RE stands for redefineses expectations,
which there's meets all, there's
exceeds, there's greatly exceeding
expectations, and then there's
redefineses. You didn't just exceed the
expectations, you redefined them. He
also had some stories to share about the
secret bonuses that only the highest
performers receive. Additional equity is
when a director chooses to give you more
RSUs, right? More stock options. Later,
he struggled with his transition to
management and eventually switched back.
I had some really bad luck actually in
my manager transition. I remember my
director, she asked me like, Simon, you
want to go back to IC? And it hit me
like, yes, yes I do. The absolute
highest rating that almost no one gets
that you don't get promoted. Why is
that? I actually believe that a lot of
people are held back in their career
because here's the full episode.
Okay, before we get into your promos to
staff in 3 years, I kind of want to go
over a little bit of the high level like
what was the thing you were working on
the space? Was it all on one team? Can
you tell me about that? My experience at
Meta has been pretty unique because I
actually stuck with the same team and
the same manager for about five and a
half years and at a company like Meta
there's usually a lot of reorganizations
happening and you end up switching
either teams or manager as a result and
it's true that our team ended up
switching a lot in terms of like our
responsibilities but we're able to keep
all the people and the manager together.
So the scope changed scope changed a lot
but I can talk through it a little bit
because it was always within the payment
space ads payments uh specifically
improving that experience. It's like a
payments growth team. Um so the primary
metric we were looking at is just
revenue right which was great uh cuz
it's very easy to to prove impact there.
We were doing a big migration in the ads
payment space. So we kind of became a
bit more of a ads payments infra uh team
for a little bit uh to support the the
migration. People across the world use
our apps very differently. Uh, for
example, in Thailand, a lot of people
purchase things on Messenger, right?
They they send bank slips back and forth
uh to prove that the purchases happened.
Um, so that was a big focus for for our
team for a while as well. I see. So,
this is within monetization, went to
like product infrastructure a little bit
and then maybe went back to product at
some point. That's right. All the same
manager direct. Yeah, sounds good. Let's
talk about the the promos. So, three
promos in 3 years and this was including
the promo block with co that we can talk
about in a bit. You know, let's be super
transparent about all the ratings and
everything if you're willing. The first
promo from 3 to four that was in 1/2 and
that was a GE rating, right? Correct.
Yeah. I seeing I mean for that to happen
you basically needed to start
immediately as an IC4 cuz you need at
least 6 months of trailing performance
before you can get promoted. How did you
start as an IC4 on that team? I do think
there are a couple important factors to
it, right? One is I was a previous
intern at Meta, which meant that I
didn't have to go through the ramp up of
learning the tools, right? And I often
see that that is one of the biggest
hurdles as people join a big company
like Meta where everything is custom.
I'd kind of like already learned how to
use Fabricator, the internal task tool,
etc. So I probably shaved off at least
four to eight weeks of of ramp up. And
then the other thing is that I had spent
some time before I joined Meta learning
so many technologies, right? And I had
built a little bit of side projects,
right? But it was primarily like
exploring, right? Like what is React?
Like can I build some basic stuff in it?
How does the type system work, right? So
that when I arrived at Meta and I
started doing the boot camp tasks to you
know learn how we actually land uh code
at Meta, I was able to move quite
quickly and also even help some of the
other new joiners um together with me uh
which immediately um increased my uh I
guess scope and impact right there.
Yeah, I think a lot of really eager,
ambitious, it's either interns or new
hires, they will reach out saying, "What
do I need to read before I come here?"
What do I need to do? And there's not a
lot of great resources out there. I kind
of wonder how effective that preparation
would even be until they got here and
the working on the internal tools. It
sounds like for you it actually was
pretty effective. How'd you find those
those early resources? The resources
primarily was just trying to build stuff
in React to be honest. Right. And also I
spent a lot of time on hackernews um and
and Reddit at that point, not so much
Reddit at this point actually. Being
aware that technologies exist and kind
of like knowing what they mean and just
the basics of how to use them really
makes everything easier. Uh cuz I
strongly believe that we're as humans or
engineers just like pattern matching
machines. The more patterns we've seen
in the past, the easier it is to to
apply them. So for example, maybe you've
never used Meta's internal JavaScript
type checker like Flow, right? But maybe
use TypeScript, right? They're not
onetoone mapping, but they're pretty
close. So if you're good with
TypeScript, you would do very well with
Flow and and vice versa. Just exploring
and being aware of different
technologies um gets you very far. You
kind of ramped up a little bit before
you even started at Meta with that with
the internship. Was the internship on a
different team then? Yes. Okay. So even
though it's a different team still all
the internal knowledge of the tools and
everything applied when you came in you
were just immediately able to land code
quickly. What was the thing that kind of
drove that that GE promo in one half?
One thing that really set me up for
success is it actually ended up joining
um a very new team. Right. So I was the
second engineer which did mean that I
did get a lot of one-on-one time with
our manager. Right. So he helped me a
lot throughout that right to ensure that
you know I got that early momentum and
had impactful projects etc. I would say
the the rating um was actually primarily
due to my impact right so we were an ads
payments team that was focusing
primarily on revenue right as our goal I
was just a second engineer we didn't
have a lot of engineers right and the
projects that I worked on right these
were the ones that brought in more than
three times of our half goal and one
important thing to note about promos at
Meta is that they're lagging right so
you really do need to show that um the
behaviors of the next level. One big
difference between IC3 and IC4 is taking
ownership of kind like the completion of
a project rather than like smaller
tasks. When I was given a task, I made
sure to bring that to conclusion and
then figure out what's the next similar
thing that we can keep working on,
right? So, it was a continuous motion of
let's get more impact out of this one
thing, right? And then maybe we, you
know, got to the the maximum impact that
we could have there and then I was
pointed towards a new area and I was
able to drive that forward. And if
something didn't go right and like the
results weren't there, then, you know,
taking ownership of figuring out why it
didn't go well and, you know, obviously
I'm new. I'm I'm seeking a lot of
assistance from others, but the
willingness and the kind of pushing that
forward um is the behavior that likely
got me to IC4. You mentioned that going
to a new team was an asset, but the the
other side is there's probably less
mentorship available if you're one of
two engineers, you're a new grad. Did
you seek that out that that team and you
know, how'd that play? Where'd you get
the mentorship from? How'd you grow in
that sense? Yeah. So when I joined Meta,
I was planning on going into an infra
team, right? So I said I had done some
research into React and stuff and I
thought that was that was good, but my
actual passion was in like C++ infra
stuff, which is what I did during my
internship. Back in the day, the way
that it worked when you joined Meta is
that you did went through boot camp and
you spoke to many different managers to
see which team would you like to join.
Um, I set up one meeting with um, Baloa,
the manager of the the team I ended up
joining. Baloa was the first manager I
spoke to and he told me that, you know,
Simon, we care about impact at Meta and
what's more impactful than revenue. So,
I ended up there, right? So, he he kind
of like lured me into it. It was more so
there was a really good feeling within
the team with the manager. We didn't
have a PM yet, but she was kind of
helping out on the side. Um but because
my manager he was uh somewhat recently
converted IC6 to manager as well. So he
had that deep technical knowledge
though. Um so he was the one that
actually guided me a lot through that
those technical decisions and I think
really grew me in other things that are
important at Meta such as like running
experiments. So my first half at Meta I
ran 20 experiments. Um and we were a
pretty small or uh within payments and
not really like used to run experiments
right. So the entire or ran 50 and I ran
20 of those, right? So kind of like I
was able to have a high velocity at the
start and I think that was a lot thanks
to the direct mentorship from my
manager. It was very technical. I see.
You mentioned that he lured you in with
impact as a new grad. Why did you care
about impact at the time? Was that for
career growth aspect or some other Yeah.
So I don't know why I had this goal but
when I joined Meta I decided for myself
I want to be IC5 within 3 years. So I
guess I overachieved there but that was
kind of my goal, right? So as I chatted
with the different managers, I told him
this, right? I was like, "Hey, I would
like to get to IC5 in 3 years, right? I
know it's ambitious, but like how could
you help me?" And Bala, you know, he
brought me to the whiteboard when he
drew up a plan of like this is what it
might look like, right? So I think he
actually did that exact same path. Um,
similar to uh to me in terms of like how
quickly he grew to six. He knew that it
was possible to grow this fast and in
some ways how to do it. I mean, he
delivered and he's a common thread
through your experience of your your
growth. So, 100% I I credit a lot of my
success and growth to to Balo. So,
definitely shout out to him. When it
comes to IC4 to IC5, this was
interesting because this took three
halves, but there was the co half which
may or may not have blocked a promo. And
you had two RE ratings, which most
people would never achieve that rating
in their career even once. It's a very
rare rating. And RE stands for
redefineses expectations, which for
reference there's there's meets all
which is great. There's exceeds even
better. There's greatly exceeding
expectations, which is pretty much the
upper bound of doing well. And then
there's redefineses. I remember when I
first heard redefineses. I was think
that is the coolest one. You
you didn't just exceed the expectations,
you redefined them. It was so insane. So
yeah, I do want to go into the RE
ratings. Um, so the first half you got
RE rating as IC4. Not only is that
impressive because it's RE rating, but
you had just gotten promoted. So it's
almost like you you leaprogged IC4
almost you were you know doing like IC5
IC6 stuff maybe immediately what drove
that RE rating that first one there's
one primary thing that drove it uh which
is impact right of course ratings
overall especially at early levels is
primarily about how much impact you can
achieve right so uh our second half in
the team we've actually recruited a few
people which I was a big part of uh
recruiting them and onboarding which is
part of the rating. But our second half,
we had a goal of let's just say many
many dozens of millions of dollars um
that we had to increase the revenue
metaphor, right? The project I drove and
worked on um overachieved even that half
goal that had a very heavy lean as to
why the redefineses. Right. Right.
Right. Makes sense where Yeah. We just
cared a lot about impact at Meta and I
guess my manager was right when he lured
me to the team saying that uh you know
we didn't care about revenue, right? Um
did you know that that project was going
to exceed the team goal by multiple like
at the beginning when I was so we we did
not know right we did have a great data
scientist um who I also really enjoyed
working with and he had you know a hunch
that it might be impactful right but I
think it's it was partly also how I went
about it right where many of these
projects initially
didn't pan out right they they were
neutral but then by by showing grit And
once again taking ownership and really
like ensuring that when something didn't
have the expected outcome, digging in to
understand why didn't it, right? Like
why didn't this work? So I can take two
different examples here. Yeah. Where we
had one project where um when an
advertiser fails a payment, right, we
obviously let them know and we asked
them, hey, you failed a payment um if
you want to keep running ads, please pay
us, right? But um that experience was
not very obvious to advertisers, right?
So we worked on improving that to make
it more obvious so that the advertisers
that want to pay us actually can. When
we first rolled out this improvement,
completely neutral, right? And we just
couldn't understand why. But we went in,
we dug into it, worked together with
data scientists to figure out why. And
we're able to update the targeting, uh
work with the designer, improve it. Um
and it uh became you know about 20% of
my impact that half. Um same thing with
another project together with this
really great DS that we had. This was
the majority of my impact that half. But
we were running a script once a day to
update some settings for advertisers,
right? And for whatever reason the
experimentation logging just didn't work
as expected. I made sure to fully
understand why it didn't work. I reached
out to the experimentation team. I
reached out to the to DS. I looked
deeply in the code to you know come up
with a hypothesis of like what's
happening. It's that behavior of full
end to end ownership of the success of a
project that had another big impact
here. Um and as a result actually this
this DS which I think at the time he
might have been five maybe six and I
think now is either a seven or an eight.
Um he left a peer feedback saying that
Simon's one of the favorite engineers um
I've worked with. Right. Right. And that
to me is still a feedback that I that I
hold dear just cuz like that to me
showed that my behaviors of truly taking
that end to end ownership is important
not just to to my success but also to
others um enjoyment of working with me.
When I was just entering the industry
and you're in experiment review, there's
a very big difference between the people
who are really exceptional and the
people who are still growing, which I
found it interesting that the the some
of the most exceptional engineers or
maybe even my manager at the time, they
were so curious about the
counterintuitive results in experiment
review. Whereas a lot of engineers who
were just kind of like, oh, this is my
future. I'm just, you know, bringing it
cuz someone told me to bring it. It
looks okay. They would stop there. But
the the really great IC's would continue
to dig and say, why is this neutral? And
at least have a explanation. I think,
you know, it's it's okay if, oh, it's
neutral because we expected it to be
neutral. There was some, you know,
something here that's just not going to
do the effect we want.
But if there's some counterintuitive
result and really digging deep and
understanding, that's often where
there's uh either an interesting
learning forge excellence, something
where it's like, oh, this is a class of
problems that's going to hurt uh the
team, something like that, or it's its
impact because there's a fix there, like
in your case, and it leads to, you know,
really outsized wins. So that that makes
a lot of sense. We had recruited I think
another five people at this point,
right? So I think the team had grown
from like the two three we were at the
very start to to eight, right? And I
took a big part in uh the recruitment of
these people but then also the the
onboarding, right? And one challenge we
had as a team is that now we actually
had one Android and one iOS engineer.
That's all we had. So and within the the
payments org, we didn't really have that
expertise either. I actually stretched
myself and started reviewing code on all
these other platforms, right? So I was
reviewing code on on Android, on iOS, on
the the main meta back end, which is
hack, you know, PHP um as well as
JavaScript, right? So I was really
stretching myself in um the the
excellence and and the the people um and
I got a lot of positive feedback in how
I do diffuse that they actually help
people grow. probably not much on the
Android and iOS side. Uh but
specifically in like the the JavaScript
side, I ensure that um as I leave
different view comments, I not only
uplevel the the codebase, but also the
the people and it took me a few halves
to like find the right um balance there
where I I got feedback that hey Simon,
you're you're being a little overbearing
in your different views, right? But
primarily I got a lot of feedback that
what Simon tells me these different
views makes me a better engineer and
like can helps me contribute more to the
team. Right. Right. Um makes sense. If
you if I had asked you throughout that
half, what rating do you think you're
going to get? Would it have been aligned
with what happened or what or did you
even think about that at all? Ratings
were just a byproduct of your work. To
be honest, I I had no idea what to
expect. I was a pretty fresh, blue-eyed
person from from Sweden coming into
Silicon Valley. Yeah. I didn't really
know what RSUs were when I joined. Um I
just looked at the salary. I was like,
"Yeah, that looks good." Um I had no
idea that like RSU was going to become,
you know, a major part of compensation,
right? Um when my for my first half when
I got my my promo, right, my manager
actually just told me, "Hey, meet me
down in the lobby." I had no idea what
to expect, right? Like we hadn't had our
PC chat yet, right? But uh we met in the
lobby. We took an Uber to a restaurant
and uh turns out that he actually has
this uh routine of whenever one of his
uh reports get a promo, he takes them
out to dinner, right? So I sat there not
knowing what to expect at all. I guess
at that point I started to suspect a
little, right? But um kind of come the
second half for the re I really had no
idea. like I I didn't know what the
expectations were really just that I
knew I was doing well but not how well.
That's one thing I missed after co
happened is no there wasn't a lot of
inerson stuff and I remember before that
my manager would come with like an
envelope and like paper and here you go.
Um and when you got the re were you what
was the reaction? I mean I was
definitely
happy right? Um, but the problem is that
it came so early in the career, right,
that it's like it was hard to
know that it was a difficult rating,
right? Where like I got in GE my first
time plus a promo. Now I got an RE, no
promo. It's like it's hard to
contextualize it when all I've seen thus
far is just like a promo plus a GE.
Obviously, my manager told me that it's
a hard one to achieve. Um, but I
actually knew someone. I'm not sure if
he got re when he was an IC3 or an IC4
in like a sister team. So I was like,
okay, maybe it's not so hard, right? So
re are really special actually. So So
you mentioned no promo. How's that
possible? You get the absolute highest
rating that almost no one gets. You
don't get promoted. Why is that? There's
a difference between promo and ratings.
And I think this becomes especially
important actually in the in the four to
five because I find that often times in
the four to five especially since we do
have that time limit to it at meta where
five is the terminal level that you need
to reach within 3 months is it something
like that. Yeah. Um where promos and
ratings are correlated but there's not a
onetoone mapping between them. Right.
where ratings is more so about what you
achieved and promos are more so about
how you achieved it. As a four, right,
the expectation is that you can drive
your project forward, right? That that's
kind of it. But as a five, you need to
take more ownership of other people and
I was starting to to touch on that a
little bit, right? In terms like
onboarding others, but I wasn't
responsible for their success or the
success of their projects. my behaviors
didn't align with those VC5 uh because I
didn't take that larger um
responsibility and scope. Was that a
question that you asked your manager
when you got the RE or you didn't think
too much about that? I think I was happy
enough with the RE to be honest where uh
I would be too
promos are all about how you're getting
it done and that you're getting it done
in a sustainable way that is expected of
the next level. But if you chanced upon
or you just did a lot of IC4 work and it
was very impactful that may not
necessarily get you closer to the promo.
Correct. I see. So then and then in the
next half uh that was the co half right.
Correct. Yeah. So during that half,
right, there was kind of like a star, I
guess you could get like a annotation in
your uh performance review, right, that
said like the first half of of COVID,
you were significantly above, which is
practically equating to a GE rating,
right? Uh because we didn't do any
official ratings. We didn't do any
promos that half, which um I remember
being a little bit sour about, right?
Because now I was like, okay, I had my
RE the first half as an IC4. I felt like
as if I would have been on track for
that um second half promo especially
knowing that I you know he didn't truly
say that I got the the annotation right
but like he he was hinting at it so I
knew that I I was doing really well
right so a little bit sour on that
obviously our careers are are long right
so like one half isn't a big deal but um
since that that half was 33% of my
career right like it felt like a like a
big loss time. Okay, then let's talk
about the next half because you got
another re. So, wait, what happened
there? How you didn't just get one, you
got two. How did you redefine
expectations a second time? Got to say
it was a little bit of a fluke slightly
easier because they did boost the the
rating somewhat from the previous one.
So, it's possible it would have been a
GE, but I was probably pretty close to
the to the line regardless. I see. I
see. And you're saying the the bump was
because they were trying to forward
credit the lack of correct. I don't
think they bumped everyone to RE that
had a GE. Um, but um I think um I was
probably on the border if I would have
gotten it otherwise. So I got the RE um
my third half um or third half is IC4
plus the IC4 to IC5 promo, right? Um and
I think the important thing here is that
my behaviors actually started to change.
Um so the team like I mentioned at the
start we were kind of pivoting between
different responsibilities right now
we've switched from being um a bit more
of an infra team back onto product uh
and we took on a new product space right
we ended up um splitting the team into
two virtual teams or two teams and we
and I took responsibility of one half of
it right so for four people plus me or
three people plus me um I was now
responsible for going from idea
completely unscoped space to completed
projects and that was a first for me. Uh
that required a lot of growth in terms
of like how I operated but this was that
big step change in terms like my scope
and responsibilities where now I'm no
longer responsible for my own output and
my own success. I'm now responsible for
the project success and the people
within it. Right. Right. Um and in the
end the product wasn't actually as
successful but we dealt with it really
well in terms of like how we behaved. Um
we ended up having a bunch of leadership
escalations up to director level you
know um with um IC8s and stuff. You know
me being an IC4 at the time um I was
getting a lot of credit for that um
communication. Why did your manager or
whoever trust you as an IC4 to lead a
pod of engineers? I and I imagine not
all those engineers were just new grads
or something. So there was some
identifying of you to lead that that was
a little bit earlier than maybe your
your experience. Why do you think that
is? So I think as a engineer there are
kind like two primary themes to me where
I am just good technically right in
terms of like the diff views etc right
where like I I just really love tech um
and in Sweden we actually choose our
major already in high school so I did
computer science since I entered high
school right so that's I think helped me
kind of like get a nice head start and
I've tried to keep ahead of that the
entire time just solid technically which
means that if there's
hairy technical issues, I can help solve
them. Uh actually regardless of platform
um often times and number two, I love
people, right? like I really enjoy
working with people uh growing people uh
ensuring that people are successful.
Obviously when um I get responsibility
kind like leading this pod right I am
responsible for the outcome of the
product the project but actually what I
find more important is the outcome of
the people that's working on it and I
think I had shown many of these
behaviors throughout um of kind of like
helping others improve um and I believe
that that was one of the big reasons why
Bala was willing to kind of give me this
responsibility um and I had been um
doing some sprint planning for a couple
people uh before once again I wasn't
really responsible for for their success
or the project success but I was
responsible for for prioritization of of
projects with them. When you mentioned
that you were leading that pod were you
meeting with these engineers one-on-one
and also talking about career with them
aside from just the the day-to-day
tasks? Mhm. A couple people I was
talking about uh career, right? But um
some of them it was more just like high
level stuff ensuring that like they're
they're happy and um they are growing on
maybe the the axis that they're lacking
in rather than like how to get to the
next level kind of thing, right? Like I
I spot a gap and I help them fill it
kind of thing. Um but I was mentoring
about I think four people that have
Yeah. Um I think one IC3 and like three
IC4s. Yeah, I remember I was an IC4 at
the time, right? Uh, and the other thing
about people, right, is that this was
the first half that I was an intern
manager. At the same time, I was an
intern peer for four different interns.
Um, that's a lot. Yeah. So, I was an
intern manager and and my intern
struggled a lot at the start. Actually,
it's one of the my proudest moments
actually ensuring that they got that
return offer. Yeah. Uh, because they
were really struggling kind of getting
them through that that finish line.
How'd you turn that around?
So if I remember correctly, it was u
like a react project um or a hack
project, one or the other, right? And it
was just some of the fundamentals that
took longer to understand and really gro
than uh you know anticipated. Sometimes
you often just need to get people over
that hump and then after that they're
totally fine, right? Um and I think at
meta that hump can sometimes be quite
high, right? I often see interns
struggling quite a bit um setting up um
our internal data model right with with
ants um that can be a very like big hump
sometimes right with her I was very
generous with my time and I think that's
um another thing that I find very
important that be be generous with your
time and in return that's going to you
know help others grow which is going to
make you a force multiplier which is
going to like give you back time later
so being generous with your time is a
very high leverage projectivity. Yes. Um
cuz it's going to work out better later.
Yes. In in most cases, there's also the
case where you invest a bunch of time
and the needle never moves and Yes.
There are definitely the cases where you
need to call it quits. Yeah. Um and I do
think that I have not yet found the
right balance. I think that I might
stick with people for longer than uh is
worth it sometimes. Yeah. Yeah. But at
least that way my conscious is clear um
throughout uh cuz I do care a lot about
each person's success. The turnaround
case that is very impactful taking
someone cuz the opposite could have
happened too. You could have saved your
time and they could have kept going the
other direction and kind of lose a
person's worth of of bandwidth. So yes.
Yes. Uh it's actually quite funny. My uh
my wife was getting a bit upset at me
with just how much time I was spending
with the intern cuz it was eating into
our dinner and like date time, right? So
yeah. Okay. So you got the the IC5 promo
double re and everything was kind of you
know it all it all made sense. You're
leading a pod. Uh and then the last
thing is you know growing from five to
six. You did that very quickly. Two
halves. Kind of want to dig in. And I
think this one's more interesting, too,
cuz the behaviors change even more than,
you know, four to five or 3 to four. So,
yeah, maybe you can tell me the story
about the promo from five to six and we
kind of dig in. So, it took me two
halves. Um, and if we look at just like
some of the behavior issues that I had
kind of like um as got promoted to five
and kind of looking forward as like what
was missing for for six, right? that
like while I was responsible for others
um I had like fully gro that right I
wasn't very good at like holding them
accountable in return right to ensure
that like things are on track and like I
wasn't very good at just like tracking
things knowing where things were etc
right so I was still operating a lot on
like a a trust model and just like
hoping that everything works out um so
that was a big gap in general so kind of
like as I went from 5 to six and my two
halves. Yeah. From four to five, I
started leading one pod. My first half
as a five, um I started leading two
pods. Given more responsibility, I'm now
leading um two pods uh with seven people
uh in total. So the the scope is
increasing for me as a result. Um which
means that I need to learn how to scale
myself, which is another important skill
set to learn as you're growing from
being responsible for a small amount of
people to a large amount of people. um
you know maybe as we're doing sprint
planning now previously I did it now
instead I you know assign um pod leads
that do it for me right or like for for
the team right where I am involved
guiding coaching um but I let others
take that uh which is another beautiful
thing because now they are growing in
return right now they're successful and
they can make it towards um whatever
goals they have I think my first half as
an IC5 where It's where I'm starting to
unlock the how to scale myself where
whether it be sprint planning, uh
whether it be recruiting onto the team,
right? Where, you know, we were still
meeting with a lot of boot campers to to
keep growing the team. It was a
different time at Meta for sure. And um
I can no longer do all of this by
myself, right? Where I um get a people
within the team was like, "Hey, we need
to coach more people." So I coach them
in like how we do outreach, how we, you
know, track the progress of each
candidate. Um, and then I might still do
the the hardest thing which might be
like that first sell call, right? Like
really get them hooked, right? But then
I have the others kind of like take
responsibility of uh the candidate
moving forward, right? So unlocking that
skill was a very kind of like step
change for me, right? Um, but still this
first half I didn't really know how to
keep others accountable for that success
where things were still slipping. Um,
and I didn't uncover it until way too
late. M um and my second half as an IC6
is then where I start to more so
get that where I'm starting to be able
to zoom out enough that I see that
either when projects are starting to
drop or people are starting to to
struggle right that there are I've set
up systems in place that can uncover
either of these problems to ensure that
people are successful and products are
successful so that either, you know,
some kind of intervention is required or
I just need to spend some time kind of
like covering a gap for a little bit. It
can be just like, oh, this person is
struggling with this one specific piece.
Well, let me as a TL step in kind of
like fix that one hairy bug and then I
know that they'll be totally fine. when
I was going for IC6 and that was the
biggest gap that of feedback that I
received which was scaling myself and
sounds like your first half you
delegated you gave people pieces of work
and you scaled yourself but then there
were maybe some gaps in assuring that
those things were successful afterwards
is that did I understand correctly yeah
I think that that's correct there was a
lot of kind of like oh the half is
ending this is not done yet wow let's
like figure out what happened and like
how I can fix it ASAP.
Um and that was I'd say pretty
systematic systematic from the time I
kind like just got to five up until kind
of like my um or like at the half I got
from four to five, right? Like this this
was a problem. My second half as a five,
this was a problem. And then kind like
the towards the end of my five to six
journey is kind of when that really
clicked. Yeah. Yeah. Um cuz I um my
second half as a five um I was given a
lot of responsibility. We the two pods I
had before right about seven people. We
had recruited some more. We ended up
splitting the team officially into two
parts right. So I now was responsible
for one part of the team which was eight
people right so responsible for ensuring
that you know they hit their goals. Um
and we did we exceeded those goals. Uh
but at the same time we spun up a
separate project uh which ended up
including um 13 people. So I was kind of
like tailing both of these at the same
time. So that really stress tested my
ability to to scale myself. Yeah. Right.
Specifically in that five to six
journey, right? Like it's the scaling
yourself. But something that is often
discussed during kind of like someone
preparing their promo packet for five to
six is like what's the deep technical
contribution, right? During my second
half here, I think I was able to balance
these two quite well, right? where the
high level stuff of like setting the
road map of uh this project right
ensuring that like we have we have clear
milestones. Um same thing with the with
the other team where you know we have uh
we have set the goals we have um
hypothesis for how we might hit those
goals um and then coaching the people to
move in that direction right at the same
time you need to show that you are a
skilled engineer right and I did this
through um a couple different ways one
was continued diffuse throughout my
career I've always valued diffuse
specifically high quality differs um
I've often been in the top three, top
five of amount of diff reviews plus the
amount of words in diff comments, which
is a metric that I really enjoy looking
at actually cuz I find that there's a
strong correlation between the amount of
words you write and the quality um that
you uh give in those diffuse. So I was
spending hours a day just like reviewing
code which I found to be a very high
leverage activity especially when you're
like in a
small to medium team because then you as
a TL can have a really good
understanding of like all the different
parts of the codebase and how they fit
together um and you can really you can
catch issues early right for example I
was reviewing you know Android iOS iOS
server which meant that when I saw that
um the Android engineer in um
implemented something this way, the iOS
engineer implemented this way, the
server engineer was trying to do it a
third way. It's like wait, hey guys,
like let's figure out like how what's
the one unified way of doing it, right?
So, different use was one very high
leverage activity in terms of like
technical contributions. Mhm. And number
two, um, on the big project that we had,
um, we were getting really close to the,
um, the milestone, but we were really
struggling to kind of get it over the
that line, right? It was, it was a
payments product, um, that crossed
between IG to Meta's main backend stack
onto the um, payments back end, which is
in C++ um, onto a third party payments
partner, right? M and we just couldn't
make it all happen, right? So I went in
as a TL. I spent many many hours just
like digging deep into the code, which
meant that I had to go from the Android
iOS code onto the um IG servers back end
onto the the meta main back end onto C++
and I had like break points all over
these code bases, right? would just show
that like I was able to work at a very
wide span but also just like very
detailed um and and go deep and solve
the the hairiest problems that we had.
You were able to hand off things but
maybe not assure their their success.
What was the the the one thing that you
switched in that half where that really
made the big difference and close that
gap? My manager uh used to say
delegation is not abdication. It means
that you may delegate whatever you want
but in the end you were responsible for
the outcome. I assumed that this person
would get it done and I I hoped they
would, right? But as I grew, I
internalized this more and I also set up
processes that helped me catch these
issues. Whether it's like a weekly um me
um sprint meeting or something where
like you catch up with people and see
like oh are they progressing and you
actually pay attention and see is the
thing they're working on actually moving
as we intended. I strongly believe
actually that every team should have a
people breakdown and a project
breakdown. Yeah. Uh because I I find
that that to be incredibly helpful where
a project um might be on track, right?
But that project might be um supported
by multiple different people. But then
when you look at the people breakdown,
it might be that oh this one person is
doing really well on the project, but
this other person is really struggling
and hasn't really landed anything for a
few weeks. And that's a huge red flag
which like if you only look at the
project level, you might be missing that
there's someone on the team struggling
um that needs your support. So when you
say abdication, you just mean that when
you hand something off for delegation,
you continue to in your mind think that
this is still my responsibility. I'm
going to deliver this. It's just it's
coming through someone. It's a a tactic
for getting it done, but it's not just
like trust and forget about it kind of
thing. You like continue to stay on top
of it. I think early in my four to five
journey um as I'm trying to scale myself
through others, I got feedback like,
"Hey, Simon, like take a step back,
right? Like you're you're stepping on my
toes like I need some room to like
implement this, right? Like you you gave
me a project just like step away for a
bit to ensure that like I can grow." I
think that's uh one of the big steps
between four and five where you actually
need to learn to let go right you can no
longer achieve everything yourself even
more so five to six where like now you
need to uh you might not even be able to
review all the code anymore right like
you you need to trust that the other
people in your team can support um the
different projects but you still verify
through them just maybe not micromanage
exactly I'm curious after you got
promoted to six because your your
trajectory was rocket ship, right? Did
you what what were you thinking in terms
of career planning? Cuz you had exceeded
your original goal. You wanted to get to
five. You got to six faster than you
know a lot of people thought. Were you
thinking about seven or did you want to
do management or were you thinking I
achieved the goal I want it's time for
personal life or something like that?
Yeah. Um I mean I was definitely you
know hungry for more, right? Uh, and I
guess I still am in some ways. Yes. Um,
but um I also recognize that like in
some ways it's a bit of a crossroads,
right? Where like now there's the option
of management and uh I guess we'll get
to this, but I did choose the manager
route for a little bit, but I struggled
a lot with that decision. My identity
was definitely part of like being a good
engineer, right? And I was so worried
about losing that 5 10 years down the
line. uh if I switch to management now
will I just become a middle manager that
have lost all their uh technical
abilities and like I've stopped
providing value and I'm just you know
existing right that was a a huge concern
of mine to be honest right so in the end
I did choose the the management route um
but ended up switching back to to IC
yeah so I mean I had a very similar
exact thinking because I love the the
building aspect of it and the technology
so how did you make that decision to
become a manager? One large part
actually is that I was still with my
same manager. The same manager that I
had since I started the company as an
IC3. He was still my manager now as an
IC6. Uh and the funny thing is that we
started together or I mean he started
before me but when I started, you know,
I was in California. Now we're actually
in London, right? We're both working in
London. So you moved with him, correct?
Yeah. So uh he sounds like a great
manager, so it's seems worth it. Truly.
Yeah. So, you know, I'm now in in
London. We're working together. Uh we're
starting up a new team. So, he he was
leading two teams. I got one of the
teams as a TL and then, you know, there
was the opportunity to become a manager
um because the team was like seven,
eight people. my manager was getting too
many direct reports and because I knew
that I had my manager support uh and
that he's been coaching me so well
throughout my entire career uh and I
find him to be an extraordinary manager
uh it felt like if I do the manager
shift doing it together with him might
be the best thing I like how he is as a
manager if I become a manager I would
like to become similar to him and thus
um now might be the time to do it.
Right. Right. Having a good manager may
be the best gift that someone could have
uh if they're very ambitious in career
and wanting to grow. And you are were
very lucky and fortunate to have such a
wonderful manager. What are the the
things that made him special as a
manager?
He cared, right? He cared about people.
He cared about projects um about impact.
He he knew the company right he I mean
by now he's been here 10 years bit more
um so when I joined he had probably been
at the company like fourish years so he
knew the process you know he he knew
everything right and he himself had had
such a rocket ship uh trajectory within
the company uh that he uh I think really
understood what I wanted to achieve. Uh
I think the other thing that really made
him stand out um as an engineering
manager is that he was probably more of
a product person really uh which is
funny because he actually just a few
months back switched as to a PM uh
within meta right so um he was really
able to set the road map of the team um
at a really great level of detail um
upwards communication downwards
communication
um which then let the engineers in the
team uh once we were uh ready to I guess
you know as he had um coached us to
really run with it right on the
engineering front and then he kept
coaching us on the the product
management and like data and and growth
front uh to ensure that like we can
become engineers that are you know
valuable to the company and one more
skill that he does very well is
communication right and it's something
that he coached us really well in
because I do believe that to be
successful at a large company as Meta,
communication is key. Written
communication especially is incredibly
high leverage. I mean we have our
internal forum workplace at Meta. If you
post a post, thousands of people can see
it. If you write effectively so that
people actually get the message uh from
what you're trying to say, it makes such
a huge difference. Um I actually believe
that a lot of people are held back in
their career because they might be doing
amazing things but they can't
communicate just how good that is. Of
course, sometimes it's like in meetings
um if people are struggling to
communicate clearly um in spoken word.
Uh but I believe that the biggest
hindrance for people might be written
communication where when they write a
post to communicate that I achieved this
project, this is why it's important.
They might just say I did this, right?
But like but why? What was the learning?
Like what did Meta or the team or the or
gain from this? And I think that's one
big gap that that people have. I agree
100%. And written versus spoken, I
agree. Written is definitely higher
leverage because the largest audience
the average engineer is speaking to is
maybe dozens of people at most. But in
written language, it can be read by, you
know, at least a hundred very simply.
And you know, over time too, it's
referenced again later. People look back
on it. it's uh used for future decisions
and you know I agree 100%. What is it
that makes an effective update or piece
of writing about your project? Like what
makes it effective? Consider that the
person that will read it will spend 5 10
seconds most make it incredibly parsible
at a glance. Yes. Right. The TLDDR,
right? Make sure it's truly a TLDDR.
Yeah. If possible include numbers,
right? like people understand the
numbers much better than you know
written words truly that's like the the
most important thing and that should be
so in workplace we kind like you know um
fold the posts uh together right when
they're too long so ensure that TLDDR is
truly above the fold so that it's it's
right there oh you're talking about the
see more yeah okay so whatever that
first thing is that they see really gets
across a strong message exactly I see
and then also make sure that when you
write the post. Um, consider the
audience or try to write the post in
different sections, target different
audiences. Um, if you try to communicate
to a large audience, let's say hundreds,
likely most of them won't have that same
technical knowledge of the specific
piece that you're working on, but they
might care about um the outcome and the
why and maybe the next steps. So I often
do, you know, like the flashy title,
TLDDR with some numbers, you know, set
the context and um then kind of like the
the impact and next steps, right? That's
kind of like always what I keep towards
the top as like the top three sections.
But then I might have like a and here's
more have all the technical details to,
you know, attract the the fellow nerds,
right? Like get the other people that
are like really interested in like the
the how, not just the why. Uh 100%. I
think that's the biggest communication
mistake that software engineers make is
they've been deep in the weeds of the
project details and then I read a post
and it's full of all this stuff of you
know I went to into this system and then
I found this line of code and then you
know it turns out that this this didn't
execute and there's an exception well
and all of that I mean that only matters
to maybe your one or two collaborator
that knows all those details and that
happens in meetings as well. Someone's
giving an update and it's just all the
stuff that I mean it matters but just
not to the people that are listening.
What's the what's the high level? Is it
on track or not? Is what was the number
movement? Why should they care in like
two lines? Like that's the most
important fix I feel. You said you were
worried about losing the technical after
having tried management. What did you
you learn? Was it actually a concern
that you lose the technical aspects? So,
I was only a manager for about a little
bit less than a year, right? So, I
didn't have the time to measure if I
would truly lose my technical ability,
right? Um, and to be honest, it was one
of the feedback I got from uh the people
I was um managing. It's like Simon step
away from the technical. So, I think I
was struggling a little bit in the IC to
manager transition and that I still
wanted to do some technical work. This
was bit of a struggle for me partially
because at the company they were trying
at the time to encourage managers to do
a bit more technical work but also if if
you've been the TL you're now the
manager you see a gap and you're like I
I really want to fill that gap. I was
really struggling there to be honest. I
got feedback on it. Uh I don't think I
fully truly corrected in the end. Yeah.
Um before I ended up switching. Uh I had
some really bad luck actually um in my
manager transition. my immediate manager
that had been with um for such a long
time um ended up in a accident. Had to
be out out of work for like three four
months, right? So no immediate u support
network there. Um my skip manager um was
on path leave, right? So okay, no
support there. Um the closest person in
the management chain management chain
was a director in California and
remember we were in London. So time
zones were hard. And this director had
come back from long-term sick leave as
well. So weren't like fully up to date
on all that had happened. Yeah. So that
was tough, right? I I was given this um
where I move into this role and pretty
immediately after lost a lot of my
strong support network. I also had two
people that wanted to grow from five to
six. Uh and I think I overpromised,
right? I was like, you know, maybe we
can make this happen. Yeah. Um, and I
think I had one of them on the right
trajectory, right? Because they were
able to kind of take my role as TL.
Um, but then for the other person, it
was hard to really slot that in. Uh, to
like get two people from five to six at
the same time in the same team of like
eight people, right, is a really tough
thing to do. I think I overpromised
there a little bit which is definitely a
learning uh if I ever transition to
management again. And um for reasons um
we also had to leave London and uh
chaotic ridiculous. Exactly. So with all
that um there was just too much going on
a lot of just like heartache in leaving
London and supporting team at the same
time. So I I got burned out a little bit
as manager just decided to move back
into IC which I've been very happy with
since. I mean, you could have also found
another manager role or without all that
chaos. What was the thing that made you
want to go back to IC specifically?
Yeah, I remember my director, she asked
me like, "Simon, do you want to go back
to IC?" And it hit me like, "Yes, yes, I
do."
I think it was more of a gut feel to be
honest. Um, just like, "Uh, all right."
I tried it. Incredibly poor timing. let
me just like take a break from it, go
back to what I know, just like get back
into the previous groove, right? And you
know, I'm totally open to management.
Um, not yet though. I think I want
another 3 to 5 years. I actually think
that I see six is a great level at Meta
specifically when it comes to like um
compared to management, right? Where
because the type of engineer I am is
that I enjoy growing others, right? So
now I actually get to spend my time
doing edge work, spend a lot of time
like mentoring and coaching others. Mhm.
And that like mentoring and coaching
becomes a bit more of a uh a bonus,
right? In terms of like my performance
evaluation, right? Right. Compared to if
I'm a manager, that becomes now like the
main thing I'm evaluated on. And you
know, not everyone's fun to coach. And
like now I can kind of pick and choose a
little bit like who and what I'd like to
coach. Yeah. Um, so I find that as an IC
that enjoys people stuff, I actually
have way more flexibility in how I apply
um that people stuff. As a manager, you
take on responsibility for everyone and
it's an unconditional support. As an IC,
you you kind of pick your project. You
know, you're you're creating scope as
IC6. So you kind of create scope that
you you want to work on and you are
helping the people you want to help. I
mean not not fully there's still some
stuff where you need to take
responsibility but there is a lot more
optionality that that makes a lot of
sense and you got burned out not
specifically because of management but
there the circumstances around it uh was
just really tough. Um I think I probably
would have stuck with it if the
circumstance had been better. Um I might
have still switched back to IC. I I find
that quite likely to be honest, but I
think I would have stuck with management
for longer before I made that switch
back. Before we fully leave your kind of
fully transparent ratings and promos. Um
I think you had mentioned that you
received DE uh once or twice throughout
your journey and DE stands for
discretionary equity. U I think it's
called AE in some cases like additional
equity. What what is that? H how does it
work? Maybe you could tell us about your
experience. Yeah. Yeah. Additional
equity um is when um a director chooses
to give you more RSUs, right? More stock
options. This happened twice in my
career. Um first time around was in my 5
to6 promo where I got a random 15
minutes calendar slot on my calendar one
day. Um I with a with a director um I
show up um he's there and he's like,
"Simon, do you know do you know why we
have this meeting?" I'm like, "I have no
idea." He's like, "Oh, no.
Uh and he told me, you know, like, hey,
yeah, like we decided to give you um
discretionary equity. Um which, you
know, I had heard about because I've
been in the company for like 3 years
now, but once again, I was pretty like
naive and new and like I didn't really
know what to expect, right? Cuz you
sometimes you go into kind of like the
internal compensation group where like
people post about their their success
and it's a huge selection selection bias
about who posts in there, right? It's
usually the people that get great
ratings that get AE. Um, so obviously
I'd seen a bunch of those posts. I was
like, "Okay, like all right, great. That
that happens, right?" So like I was
incredibly humbled, right? And like it
felt really good. Um, but I didn't like
understand it really. But I guess I, you
know, I got in um great ratings
throughout. Um, and since I started as
an IC3, I assumed that maybe um, they
were worried about some attrition given
um, that my stock options when I started
probably quite a bit lower compared to
what it would be for for an IC6. I see.
So that first DE was it wasn't
gamechanging. It just kind of gave you
maybe a little bit more than market. Is
that right? Yeah, I believe so. Um it
was a bit hard to know at the time
because the meta stock had just crashed
which is great now when it has not
crashed. Um that was actually similar
with the second um AE uh that I got a
year later. Um so I've been IC6 for a
year. I guess I just transitioned to to
management. Yeah. Um and I ended up
getting uh my second AE. Mhm. I believe
it's primarily due to the success of the
team I took over. Right. So I I moved to
London, right? took over part of the
team. We shipped the product in a much
faster timeline than anticipated, right?
And it was a company priority as so many
things are at the company. Um, but we
executed well and like we got it done,
right? Um, so I think that the success
of that uh and the behaviors I showed uh
were a large part as why I got that
second AE. Um, and I would say that
these two combined have definitely had a
large impact on my total comp and what
it would be compared to normal market
rate. When you see a 15minute no agenda
meeting from some senior director you
never talked to. Did what did you think
when you saw that on your calendar? I
don't even know, man. Like it's uh I I
honestly had no idea what to expect. I
was a little sweaty going in. I was
like, "All right, what's what's going to
happen here?" Turns out it was a good
one. So yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah, I have a
friend who, you know, this is happening
to and he's like, I think I'm going to
get fired cuz it's like you you never
get a meeting like that. So, you
mentioned you were you were an intern,
but also at some point you told me you
were an intern director, too. So, you
kind of seen internships on both sides
of it. What's something that is like
the, you know, top things to keep in
mind or like the the 8020 tips that
Yeah. you see separate the best interns
from the people who are not as good.
Yes. Let me briefly touch on my history
when it comes to to interns, right? So,
I was an intern to start. Um, and
honestly, I didn't do very well. I think
I was very close to not getting an
offer. Um, luckily I'm here today
because I did get the offer. Uh, but I
think that I didn't do that well and I
think maybe we'll cover that. But then I
was an intern manager twice. Uh the
first time around I had an intern that
um like I mentioned went from kind of
meets most expectations to actually
meeting and getting a return offer. Um
sec and and that at the same time I was
a peer intern for interns. The second
time around uh I had an intern um
rockstar intern, right? Like we had a
couple um new hire IC3s at the same time
and my intern was coaching the IC3s,
right? Like Yeah. How's that? What? He
he was just so good at JavaScript, so
good at uh React that like he blew
through everything and was like coaching
the others like this is how you do it.
What university? It was over in Mexico.
Okay. So, yeah, it's and I asked by the
way cuz I had I had a lot of interns as
well and I noticed the ones that come
from Waterlue were just like the water
ones are great. They came in and they're
like I icy for I'm like you know how to
do everything already. Then I had two
summers or I guess one winter and one
summer that I was an intern director,
right? And the responsibility of an
intern director is that you practically
manage 10 intern managers. So you as the
intern director is responsible that the
intern manager actually produces a solid
uh project plan. Um and then you do
three check-ins with the intern
managers. You do a three-we check-in
making sure that the intern is ramping
up all right. You do the midpoint
checking to make sure like are things
like on track for the project. and then
the final check-in where you know ahead
of the the final review. Um so on to
your question of like what are some of
the the things that stand out between
really solid interns maybe interns that
that don't make it. The simplest way to
look at it, right, is like velocity in
some ways, right? Like velocity is
incredibly important, right? Because the
main measure of success for an intern is
did you complete your intern projects.
That is the primary thing we look at. Of
course, it's important how you do it,
but if you didn't do it, then that's
almost like a a fail by itself.
Obviously, there are safeguards to see
like was the project just like
completely misscoped, right? But uh
hopefully throughout the process that's
been like corrected already. Um so
velocity is incredibly important, right?
And with that comes trying to do a fast
ramp up, right? And I think a lot of
interns that don't make it don't ask
enough questions early on. Whether
you're an intern, whether you're an IC3,
whether you're like joining a new team,
those first couple weeks are so
important to like utilize your ability
to be dumb, right? To like ask those
dumb questions, right? like it's the
most valuable time that you have because
the expectations of you are practically
zero. So you can ask people however much
you want. And this is something that I
kept repeating to um interns I had as
well as like IC3's joining especially
just like if you have a question that
takes you more than like 30 minutes to
an hour like ping me please right like
if you keep spending an hour on like all
these small questions that like we could
resolve in 30 seconds like you will not
be successful right so please please
ping questions right it's incredibly
important especially early on because
it's very different to ask a question of
like oh how do I do the super basic
thing week one compared to week six,
right? Like please get that done early.
Um it's very uh it will really help your
velocity. And another thing here is that
the the intern program at Meta is set up
that you have your intern manager and
then you have usually two peers but
sometimes more. Also do take advantage
of your peers uh for two reasons. Um one
reason is maybe you're asking too many
questions. Your managers just can't deal
with them all. Right? So, uh maybe have
a chat group with, you know, uh your
inter manager plus peers. Make sure you
can ask questions in there. They can
kind of like load balance between
themselves, right? Um and number two is
that when we look at intern performance,
we actually we obviously primarily look
at the feedback from the intern manager,
but the peer feedback from the peers you
have are two other critical pieces of
input. Um and sometimes when there's
insufficient amount of evidence of um
you know the right behaviors and such
then inter managers inter directors we
need to go in do a lot of digging to to
clarify that right but if your peers
know you they know your project they
know what you're doing how you're doing
it um that makes everything much much
easier um and they can uh vouch for you
much better. You talked about the
velocity and one immediate gut reaction
is okay what if I work twice the hours
to get it done and I think some people
might hear that oh if you're if you're
barely meeting expectations but you're
working crazy hours then you know you
might get penalized or something like is
do you do you have any thoughts on on
that? We do try to get a sense of just
like how much someone is working. Like
is this feasible in the long term? If
someone's just on the line and we see
that like they're pushing diffs at like
6:00 a.m. but also 3:00 a.m. like every
day, right? Like that's a huge red flag
that like this person might not be able
to like sustain this for very long. Uh
and I'd say it's primarily an indicator
when they're just around that line. But
the the other thing is that not just for
for interns, right? But just like for
for any employee, engineer, right? Like
taking care of yourself is important,
right? I truly believe that you need to
take care of like mind and body to be a
successful person. To me, working out is
incredibly important. I I journal every
day, right? I make sure that like I have
my focus time in the morning where I can
like do focus work uh instead of just
like being stuck in meetings, right? And
like these rituals are something that
like ensures that I function
effectively. And obviously I've had
times where like um specifically
actually between 5 to 6 um trying to
solve that like very hairy bug. I was
doing like 12 14 hour days like for a
week and a half straight. That was
tough, right? But like it was worth
doing like a short sprint of like really
hard work. Um but I I know I couldn't
keep that up. I was skipping my
workouts. I was having way too much
coffee and I could just feel my mind
every morning just like slowing down,
right? So, of course, you can like put
in more hours, but just try to be
intentional about it to ensure that like
you can't put in more hours the entirety
of it. Um, but to reach a specific
milestones at times um could be one way
of achieving that. In your ambitious
growth, you had points where you're
sprinting, but you were not your steady
state was never a ridiculous health
sacrificing kind of grind. Um, what what
is that peak steady state that you've
you've learned you can maintain like
maybe an hours per week? Uh, I probably
average like 50 hours um a weekish. Um
like I I'm a morning person. So um I
wake up, I have my coffee, walk the dog,
uh work out, and then you know I maybe
start work. And then some days maybe
that's like 7:30, 8:00. Um and maybe end
up working till like 6:00 p.m. because I
need to um have meetings with like um
California. Right. Right. Right. Right.
Um so some days are longer, some days
are shorter. I also just like really
enjoy what I do. um and like the team I
work with. So I
switched teams somewhat recently
specifically because I was losing the
energy I had on like that same amount of
hours, right? Where um those same 50
hours starting to like really feel like
a grind, right? Like and I just couldn't
understand why, right? So I had to do
quite a bit of self-reflection to
understand why that might be. Yeah. It
was simply because I was like losing the
interest in that one area. And one of
the great things about Meta is that huge
company and they're also very flexible
about internal mobility. So I was able
to switch to to a new team and an infra
team and um honestly it's been a lot of
fun. Got a lot of my fire back and I
just like feel like I the quality of
work I'm able to produce is
significantly different when um I have
that interest in fire compared to like
just chugging along. I see. No, that
makes sense. So, it sounds like you're
saying work life balance is um somewhat
tied to your interest and motivation in
the work. Like sounds like you could you
could work 20 hours a week on something
you hate and that could feel worse than
50 hours a week on something that you're
really passionate about. I see. in my
career when I was really grinding for
promos and things I felt that I had work
life balance even though I was working a
lot of hours. Yeah. Cuz it's if you love
it then it's not really I mean you
that's cliche but you know it it does
not feel like so much work. So you know
for this last bit of the conversation I
kind of just want to reflect on your
career a bit and kind of ask you some
higher level stuff looking back. So, you
know, when it comes to the whole thing
so far, where did most of the growth
come from? Like, what were the things,
let's say I'm trying to reverse engineer
your career growth, what were the the
factors that led to that growth? I mean,
I think the overall word is like
ownership, right? And then like there's
a million things within. I think
ownership can be in the small, right?
like I ensure that this task gets done
or it can be I own the success of this
team right but if you start talking
especially about like early career uh
people right then like ownership means
that you you ensure the success of your
one thing right and to me I find that
this actually requires a lot of
curiosity and we have this saying at
meta of like nothing at meta is someone
else's problem the way that I interpret
that right is that like if you find an
issue right? That's like blocking you.
You don't necessarily have to wait for
the other team to tell you why you're
getting blocked. Read the code. Like
that's one of the great things about a
monor repo. Just like read the code,
read the diffs. Why did they add it?
Like what's the the reasoning? Can we
change it? Like come up with a a brief
proposal, right? And like research your
your questions or just like approach
ahead of time um to be able to move
forward. That kind of curiosity uh slash
ownership slash um you know not
accepting being blocked uh I think is
really critical for that um fast growth
especially early on. Now it's no longer
just like that one piece of code. Maybe
it's like um collaboration with a cross
functional partner like why is that not
working? Let's understand their
intention, right? Like let's be
empathetic. Like why is someone behaving
a certain way? Like are they getting
evaluated on on this one metric that
you're regressing, right? Like trying to
be kind and understand others. Um I
think is also a really other important
piece. Yeah. And it sounds like as your
career grew that umbrella of ownership
just kind of kept expanding, kept
expanding. And I imagine it even
continues further. or if you were like a
IC8 you like I care about what these 300
people are doing and that it's
successful. So yeah, it's interesting
you say when I ask you that question the
answer is kind of a non-technical
behavior. It's you know of ownership.
When you think about a successful
engineer, do what percent of it I know
it's kind of hard to quantify, but what
percent of it is non-technical stuff and
what percent of it is technical stuff
that leads to kind of career growth? I
think you can be incredibly successful
with just a baseline level of technical
skills. You need to be able to know how
to get the task done, right? Um, but you
can totally get to IC5 without like
being able to be like the the true um I
can solve any problem thrown my way kind
of person, right? like if you can get
your stuff done and like your cont
overall contributions of like chatting
with the designer uh pulling the data um
you know uh collaborating with others
like you don't need much more than that
like baseline level of like I can ensure
that like what is given to me can be
executed and like done in a high enough
quality way. I see. Okay. Okay. So, it
sounds like technical skills needed up
to a point but past that point
diminishing returns and the
non-technical skills are kind of what
really differentiates and grows people
quickly I would say. So, um with the one
caveat of like there are some people are
just like so technically talented that
like that just like outweighs
everything, right? So, like there are
obviously the edge cases there, right?
But to I do think that like soft skills
is incredibly important for a fast
career because people need to enjoy
working with you for them to kind of
give you those opportunities to grow to
trust you. You've been at Meta your
entire career at this point which in
this industry is unusual. What is the
thing that's kept you at Meta for so
long?
bit of a copout answer, but people is
definitely a big part of it, right? Like
I do really love the people at Meta. Um
my manager obviously, right? U but also
my my co-workers, right? And I think
this was especially true actually um in
my first team, right, where I joined as
a second engineer. We ended up growing
the team to like 16 people before we
like split into two, right? And since I
was a large part of uh recruiting there,
honestly, like it felt like a bit of a
family, right? like it was it was a
really happy supportive environment. Um
to be honest, a lot of people we hired
were also like straight out of college.
Like it was a very like young fun um
thing, especially since I was just out
of college, too, right? So, it was a
really just like welcoming, happy
experience. Obviously, I'm not no longer
straight out of college, but still, I
really enjoy my co-workers. I find that
people are mostly empathetic with each
others, right? Like people understand
others reasons and we try to be kind to
each other and people are just really
good technically too, right? Um so
people is definitely like one big part,
right? Why I'm staying at Meta, right? U
number two is that I find that the
flexibility of Meta is also quite
incredible, right? In terms of like
internal mobility, I've been working in
um California. Um so I worked in um
Menlo Park to start which is the HQ
during co was down in LA. I went back to
SF you know did a year in um London um
came back this time to New York. Um so
just like that flexibility in terms of
like global location has been really
great but also like internal projects.
Obviously my first team it was actually
quite a bit of forced movement in terms
of like what we focused on. But now like
I mentioned I was losing my drive. the
hour starting to feel like a real drag,
a real slug and I figured, you know,
like I need to change something up. I I
did consider going elsewhere. Uh but I
figured let's give Meta another shot,
right, and like see what's up. And I
joined this new team uh in the um ID
server infra and it's been great. Like
once again, people are great. Uh I'm
learning so much. I can go incredibly
deep technically, which is something
that's I love nerding out about. a lot
of those like check boxes as to like
what makes me tick um just like keep
appearing within meta. Um and thus I
don't have like a strong drive to seek
elsewhere. Uh which you know might
change in the future. Um I find that
there are some things you just can't um
experience at meta but um I haven't
reached a point uh yet. Yeah. No, that
makes sense. There there was someone
that I worked with who was exceptionally
senior you know everything was going
well at meta and I was thinking you know
have you ever considered leaving and he
said actually he considers leaving every
year not not from a perspective I don't
like it here but more of like a
housekeeping of you know you consider it
and if it turns out I am happiest where
I am now that gives you even more
confidence that this is the right place
I'm doing the right thing and all that.
So, okay. And then the last question,
the the question I want to ask is if you
were to go back in time, you're talking
to yourself, right? When you had
graduated and joined Meta and you give
yourself advice, what would that advice
be? Be curious and like nothing else
someone else's problem. Take ownership,
right? And obviously when you're new,
you got to keep in mind how much time
you spend on each thing, right? Similar
to like the intern, right? like ask a
lot of questions early on like get that
velocity right. But once you got that
velocity right and that like baseline
level of um productivity start asking
these questions right like why was this
done this way within the codes become a
bit of like a archaeologist to
understand like why certain decisions
were made if it's blocking you don't
just say oh it is this way therefore it
will always be this way uh kind of like
question those early decisions because
especially at a big company like Meta
there are layers and layers and layers
of tech debt and just like overall
decisions that may may no longer hold.
There are a lot of like debt experiments
lying around the codebase and like maybe
you can just like clean that up that
will make your things easier. Take
ownership, be curious and um nothing
else someone else's problem. Okay. Well,
thanks for the interview. Is there
anyone you wanted to shout out before we
end? Yes, I promised Chris u that is
covering my own call shift right now to
give him a shout out. So, thank you
Chris for covering my own call.
Awesome. Thanks. so much for this this
interview, Simon. Was really looking
forward to it. Someone that had worked
with you said you were, you know, one of
their favorite people that you've
they've ever worked with. So, thanks for
for giving to the community. Appreciate
it. Yeah. All right. Thank you very
much, Ryan. Hey, thanks for watching the
show. I don't sell anything or do
sponsorships, but if you want to
support, you can subscribe on YouTube or
you can leave a review on Spotify. And
I'm always looking for new guests to
interview. So, if anyone comes up who
you think you really want to hear their
career story, uh, let me know and I'll
try to reach out to them and get them on
the show. Thanks for listening as always
and I'll see you next time.